<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Daniel Padfield</title>
    <link>/categories/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Daniel Padfield</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Daniel Padfield</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Animate your Strava activities in R using rStrava and gganimate</title>
      <link>/post/animate-your-strava-activities-using-rstrava-and-gganimate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/animate-your-strava-activities-using-rstrava-and-gganimate/</guid>
      <description>Getting started with rStrava rStrava is an R package that allows you to access data from Strava using the Strava API. Some of the functions of rStrava scrape data from the public Strava website but to access your own data you will need a Strava profile and an authentication token. Details on obtaining your unique token can be found on the rStrava homepage. In addition to this key, we use rgbif::elevation() to calculate the elevation of each route.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysing your own Strava data in R using rStrava</title>
      <link>/post/analysing-your-own-strava-data-in-r-using-rstrava/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/analysing-your-own-strava-data-in-r-using-rstrava/</guid>
      <description>Over the last 4 years I have consistently cycled around or over 2000 km a year around Cornwall. Almost all of these rides have been uploaded to Strava which has a suite of nice ways to visualise your performance and each ride.
However, the ride data on Strava is mine, I have literally created it, and as such I looked for a way of accessing all of that beautiful data. One way would be to download all your .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In search of the hilliest parkrun in the UK</title>
      <link>/post/in-search-of-the-hilliest-parkrun-in-the-uk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/in-search-of-the-hilliest-parkrun-in-the-uk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bootstrap non-linear regression with purrr and modelr</title>
      <link>/post/bootstrapping-non-linear-regressions-with-purrr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/bootstrapping-non-linear-regressions-with-purrr/</guid>
      <description>This post was updated on the 02/03/2018 to reflect changes to nls.multstart.
Introduction For my first academic publication, a reviewer asked for the \(r^{2}\) values of the thermal performance curves I fitted using non-linear regression. I bowed to the request as is often the case with reviewer comments, but would now resist as the \(r^{2}\) is not necessarily an effective goodness of fit measure for non-linear regression (see this SO answer).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fitting non-linear regressions with broom, purrr and nls.multstart</title>
      <link>/post/fitting-non-linear-regressions-with-broom-purrr-and-nls.multstart/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/fitting-non-linear-regressions-with-broom-purrr-and-nls.multstart/</guid>
      <description>This post was updated on the 02/03/2018 to reflect changes to nls.multstart.
Introduction With my research, I often use non-linear least squares regression to fit a model with biologically meaningful parameters to data. Specifically, I measure the thermal performance of phytoplankon growth, respiration and photosynthesis over a wide range of assay temperatures to see how the organisms are adapted to the temperatures they live at.
These thermal performance curves generally follow a unimodal shape and parameters for which are widely used in climate change research to predict whether organisms will be able to cope with increasing temperatures.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Doing local BLAST searches on sanger sequence data in R</title>
      <link>/post/using-blast-on-sanger-sequences-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/using-blast-on-sanger-sequences-in-r/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Moving to a microbiology group has meant I now have loads of interesting genomic and sequencing data to play with!
One common task we have when we start with some new natural communities is to work out what is in there! We plate the samples out, look at their colony morphology, but colonies can be picked and sequenced using sanger sequencing. Once you have your sequencing data back, you can check your sequence against a database to look at the taxonomic identity of the picked colonies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing nlsLoop</title>
      <link>/post/introducing-nlsloop/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/introducing-nlsloop/</guid>
      <description>Introduction So you have data you want to fit to a non-linear model…
This blog post assumes you have a non-linear model formulation you want to fit to non-linear data and are aware of the excellent nlme package by Pinheiro and Bates and their book that nicely explains how to use it. This would be my first port of call if you want to understand the simplicities and complexities of fitting non-linear models and mixed effect models in general.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>